When I was a young boy,
عندما كنت طفلاً صغيراً،
I used to gaze through the microscope of my father
كنت أنظر في الميكروسكوب الخاص بوالدي
at the insects in amber that he kept in the house.
الى الحشرات الموجودة في العلبة التي احتفظ بها في المنزل.
And they were remarkably well preserved,
وقد كانو محفوظين جيدا بطريقة ملحوظة،
morphologically just phenomenal.
شكلهم الظاهري غير اعتيادي.
And we used to imagine that someday,
وقد كنا نتخيل أنهم ذات يوم
they would actually come to life
سوف يعودون للحياة
and they would crawl out of the resin,
وسيهربون من علبة التحنيط،
and, if they could, they would fly away.
وعندها، سوف يطيرون بعيداً.
If you had asked me 10 years ago whether or not
لو سألتني قبل 10 سنوات من الآن..
we would ever be able to sequence the genome of extinct animals,
هل سيكون بإمكاننا أن نسلسل الشفرة الجينية للحيوانات المنقرضة،
I would have told you, it's unlikely.
لكن قلت لك ، من غير المحتمل .
If you had asked whether or not we would actually be able
لو كان سؤالك : هل سيكون بإمكاننا ..
to revive an extinct species,
أن نعيد فصيلة منقرضة الى الحياة،
I would have said, pipe dream.
لكنت قلت أنها أحلام وهمية.
But I'm actually standing here today, amazingly,
لكنني أقف اليوم هنا، بشكل مدهش،
to tell you that not only is the sequencing
لأقول لك، بأنه ليس فقط تسلسل
of extinct genomes a possibility, actually a modern-day reality,
الجينات المنقرضة أصبح ممكناً، وواقعاً في أيامنا،
but the revival of an extinct species is actually within reach,
ولكن أيضاً إعادة فصائل منقرضة الى الحياة أصبح في الواقع في متناول أيدينا،
maybe not from the insects in amber --
قد لا يكون عن طريق الحشرات في علبة التحنيط --
in fact, this mosquito was actually used
في الحقيقة، هذه البعوضة قد ألهمت
for the inspiration for "Jurassic Park" —
صانعي فيلم حديقة الديناصورات --
but from woolly mammoths, the well preserved remains
ولكن عن طريق حيوان الماموث الصوفي، البقايا المحفوظة جيداً
of woolly mammoths in the permafrost.
للماموث في الجليد.
Woollies are a particularly interesting,
هذه الحيوانات مثيرة للإتمام بشكل خاص،
quintessential image of the Ice Age.
الصورة المثالية للعصر الجليدي.
They were large. They were hairy.
لقد كانت ضخمة، و مشعرة.
They had large tusks, and we seem to have
ذي أنياب كبيرة، ويبدو أنه لدينا
a very deep connection with them, like we do with elephants.
تفاهم عميق معهم، كما الحال بيننا وبين الفيلة.
Maybe it's because elephants share
ربما لأننا لدينا مع الفيلة
many things in common with us.
عدة أشياء مشتركة.
They bury their dead. They educate the next of kin.
إنهم يدفنون موتاهم، يربّون الأقرباء.
They have social knits that are very close.
لديهم روابط اجتماعية قوية جداً.
Or maybe it's actually because we're bound by deep time,
أو قد يكون ذلك لأن لدينا ماض مشترك،
because elephants, like us, share their origins in Africa
فالفيلة، مثلنا، أصولهم تعود لأفريقيا
some seven million years ago,
منذ قرابة ال7 ملايين سنة الماضية،
and as habitats changed and environments changed,
ومع تغير الظروف والبيئة،
we actually, like the elephants, migrated out
رحلنا عن أفريقيا كما فعلت الفيلة
into Europe and Asia.
باتجاه أوروبا و آسيا.
So the first large mammoth that appears on the scene
إذاً، أول ماموث ترونه
is meridionalis, which was standing four meters tall
هو meridionalis, كان طوله وهوه يقف 4 أمتار.
weighing about 10 tons, and was a woodland-adapted species
يزن حوالي ال10 أطنان، وقد كان مكيّفا ليعيش في الغابات.
and spread from Western Europe clear across Central Asia,
وانتشر من غربي أوروبا الى آسيا الوسطى
across the Bering land bridge
عبر جسر بيرينج البرّي
and into parts of North America.
الى أجزاء من شمالي أميركا.
And then, again, as climate changed as it always does,
وثمّ، مرة أخرى، ومع تغير المناخ كما يفعل دائماً،
and new habitats opened up,
ومع وجود مواطن جديدة،
we had the arrival of a steppe-adapted species
وصل لدينا نوع جديد مكيّف مع السهول
called trogontherii in Central Asia
يدعى trogontherii، في آسيا الوسطى
pushing meridionalis out into Western Europe.
مُبعداً الmeridionalis الى أوروبا الغربية.
And the open grassland savannas of North America
والمساحات الواسعة من السافانا في شمالي أميركا
opened up, leading to the Columbian mammoth,
فتحت موطناً للماموث الكولومبي،
a large, hairless species in North America.
نوع آخر ضخم و عديم الشعر في أميركا الشمالية.
And it was really only about 500,000 years later
لم يكن إلا بعد 500 ألف عام حتى
that we had the arrival of the woolly,
وصل لدينا الماموث الصوفيّ،
the one that we all know and love so much,
الوحيد الذي نعرفه جيعاً ونحبّه كثيراً،
spreading from an East Beringian point of origin
منتشراً من شرقي بيرينغين، المنشأ
across Central Asia, again pushing the trogontherii
عبر آسيا الوسطى، ومجدداً، مبعداً ال trogontherii
out through Central Europe,
خارجاً الى أوروبا الوسطى،
and over hundreds of thousands of years
وخلال مئات آلاف السنين
migrating back and forth across the Bering land bridge
مهاجراً من وإلى ،عبر جسر بيرغين البريّ
during times of glacial peaks
خلال أوقات الإنهيارات الجليدية
and coming into direct contact
ليقابل مباشرةً
with the Columbian relatives living in the south,
الأقرباء الكولومبيون في الجنوب،
and there they survive over hundreds of thousands of years
وهناك يعيشون لمئات آلاف السنين
during traumatic climatic shifts.
خلال التحولات المناخية الصعبة.
So there's a highly plastic animal dealing with great transitions
إذاً لدينا هذا الحيوان المرن للغاية، الذي يتعامل مع تغييرات عظيمة
in temperature and environment, and doing very, very well.
في الحرارة والبيئة، ويتعامل معها بشكل جيد جداً.
And there they survive on the mainland until about 10,000 years ago,
وهناك يعيش على اليابسة قبل 10،000سنة من الآن،
and actually, surprisingly, on the small islands off of Siberia
وفي الحقيقة وبشكل مفاجئ، يعيش على جُزرٍ صغيرة في سيبيريا
and Alaska until about 3,000 years ago.
وآلاسكا ، حتى قبل 3،000 سنة من الآن.
So Egyptians are building pyramids
المصريون يبنون الأهرامات
and woollies are still living on islands.
والماموث الصوفيّ مازال يعيش على هذه الجزر.
And then they disappear.
ثمّ ، يختفي.
Like 99 percent of all the animals that have once lived,
حوالي ال99 بالمئة من الحيوانات التي عاشت من قبل،
they go extinct, likely due to a warming climate
انقرضت، الأرجح بسبب احترار المناخ
and fast-encroaching dense forests
والزحف السريع للغابات الكثيفة
that are migrating north,
المتجهة شمالاً،
and also, as the late, great Paul Martin once put it,
ولكن أيضاً ، كما فسّر العظيم بول مارتين مرة،
probably Pleistocene overkill,
ربما، طول العصر الجليدي،
so the large game hunters that took them down.
وبالتالي الصيادين الذين قضوا عليهم .
Fortunately, we find millions of their remains
لحسن الحظ ، نجد الملايين من بقاياهم
strewn across the permafrost buried deep
منتشرة في الجليد مدفونة عميقاً
in Siberia and Alaska, and we can actually go up there
في سيبيريا و آلاسكا، ويمكننا في الحقيقة الذهاب إلى هناك
and actually take them out.
واستخراجهم.
And the preservation is, again,
وهي، مرة أخرى
like those insects in [amber], phenomenal.
كتلك الحشرات في العلبة، محفوظة بشكل رائع.
So you have teeth, bones with blood
لديك أسنان، عظام مع دماء
which look like blood, you have hair,
والتي تبدو كالدماء ، لديك شعر،
and you have intact carcasses or heads
ولديك أيضاً جثث سليمة ، أو رؤوس
which still have brains in them.
والتي مازالت تحوي دماغ داخلها.
So the preservation and the survival of DNA
إذاً فالحماية والمحافظة على الحمض النووي سليماً
depends on many factors, and I have to admit,
يعتمد على عوامل عدة ، وعليّ أن أعترف،
most of which we still don't quite understand,
معظمه مازلنا غير قادرين على فهمه،
but depending upon when an organism dies
ولكن بالإعتماد على زمن موت جسم
and how quickly he's buried, the depth of that burial,
والسرعة التي تمّ دفنه بها ، عمق الدفن،
the constancy of the temperature of that burial environment,
و ثبات درجة حرارة بيئة الدفن،
will ultimately dictate how long DNA will survive
سوف تبيّن في نهاية المطاف إلى متى سيظل الحمض النووي سليماً
over geologically meaningful time frames.
خلال مدة زمنية مجدية من الناحية الجيولوجية.
And it's probably surprising to many of you
وقد يكون مفجائاً لمعظمكم
sitting in this room that it's not the time that matters,
في هذه القاعة، عندما لا يكون الوقت هو المهم،
it's not the length of preservation,
ولا طول فترة الحفاظ على الجسم،
it's the consistency of the temperature of that preservation that matters most.
إنها ثبات درجة الحرارة هي العامل الأكثر أهمية.
So if we were to go deep now within the bones
إذاً ، إذا دخلنا الآن الى داخل العظام
and the teeth that actually survived the fossilization process,
والأسنان التي نجت من عملية التحجر،
the DNA which was once intact, tightly wrapped
سنجد أن الحمض النووي الذي كان مترابطاً و ملفوفاً بإحكام
around histone proteins, is now under attack
حول بروتينات الهستون ، قد أصبح معرضاً لخطر الهجوم
by the bacteria that lived symbiotically with the mammoth
من البكتيريا التي عاشت بتناغم مع الماموث
for years during its lifetime.
لسنوات خلال حياته.
So those bacteria, along with the environmental bacteria,
هذه البكتيريا، مع البكتيريا البيئية ،
free water and oxygen, actually break apart the DNA
تحرر الماء والأوكسيجين ، تعمل على تفكيك الحمض النووي
into smaller and smaller and smaller DNA fragments,
الى أجزاء أصغر وأصغر وأصغر،
until all you have are fragments that range
حتى لا يبقى سوى سلسلة تتراوح
from 10 base pairs to, in the best case scenarios,
بين 10 أجواز رئيسية إلى - في أفضل الحالات-
a few hundred base pairs in length.
بضع مئات من الأجواز الرئيسية بالطول.
So most fossils out there in the fossil record
لذا، معظم الأحافير الموجودة في السجل الأحفوري
are actually completely devoid of all organic signatures.
في الحقيقة خالية تماماً من جميع الدلائل العضوية.
But a few of them actually have DNA fragments
ولكن القليل منهم حقيقةً يحوي على أجزاء من الحمض النووي
that survive for thousands,
الذي نجى لآلاف،
even a few millions of years in time.
بل حتى لملايين السنين.
And using state-of-the-art clean room technology,
وباستخدام أحدث ما توصلت إليه التكنلوجيا،
we've devised ways that we can actually pull these DNAs
أوجدنا طرقاً تمكننا من سحب هذا الحمض النووي
away from all the rest of the gunk in there,
من ما تبقى من المواد اللزجة هناك ،
and it's not surprising to any of you sitting in the room
وليس من المدهش لكم أنتم الموجودين هنا
that if I take a mammoth bone or a tooth
أنه إذا أخذت عظمة أو سنّ ماموث
and I extract its DNA that I'll get mammoth DNA,
واستخرجت منه الDNA، فإنني سأحصل على DNA الخاص بالماموث،
but I'll also get all the bacteria that once lived with the mammoth,
ولكن أيضاً سأحصل على كل البكتيريا التي عاشت يوماً مع الماموث،
and, more complicated, I'll get all the DNA
و أيضاً، بشكل معقّد أكثر، سأحصل على كل الDNA
that survived in that environment with it,
الذي نجا في تلك البيئة معه ،
so the bacteria, the fungi, and so on and so forth.
وبالتالي، البكتيريا، والفطريات، وهلمّ جراً.
Not surprising then again that a mammoth
وبالتالي ليس مدهشاً، أن ماموثاً
preserved in the permafrost will have something
محفوظاً في الجليد سيكون لديه حوالي
on the order of 50 percent of its DNA being mammoth,
ال50 بالمئة من حمضه النووي عبارة عن حمض نووي تابع للماموث
whereas something like the Columbian mammoth,
بينما ، كائن كالماموث الكولومبي،
living in a temperature and buried in a temperate environment
يعيش في جوّ حار و دُفن في بيئة حارة
over its laying-in will only have 3 to 10 percent endogenous.
خلال فترة دفنه لن يبقى له إلا ثلاث أو عشرة بالمئة من حمضه النووي.
But we've come up with very clever ways
لكننا وجدنا طرقاً ذكية جداً
that we can actually discriminate, capture and discriminate,
تمكننا من التفرقة، والتقاط و تمييز
the mammoth from the non-mammoth DNA,
الحمض النووي الخاص بالماموث عن غيره،
and with the advances in high-throughput sequencing,
ومع التقدم في التسلسل العالي السرعة،
we can actually pull out and bioinformatically
يمكننا فعلاً سحب وبطريقة معلوماتية حيوية
re-jig all these small mammoth fragments
هزهزة كل هذه الأجزاء الصغيرة التابعة للماموث
and place them onto a backbone
ووضعها على صبغيات العمود الفقري
of an Asian or African elephant chromosome.
لفيل آسيوي أو أمريكي.
And so by doing that, we can actually get all the little points
وبفعل هذا، يمكننا الحصول على جميع النقاط الصغيرة
that discriminate between a mammoth and an Asian elephant,
التي تمّيز بين الماموث والفيل الآسيوي،
and what do we know, then, about a mammoth?
مالذي نعرفه إذاً عن الماموث ؟
Well, the mammoth genome is almost at full completion,
حسناً، السلسلة الجينية للماموث أُنجزت تقريباً،
and we know that it's actually really big. It's mammoth.
ونعلم أنها فعلاً كبيرة، إنه ماموث !
So a hominid genome is about three billion base pairs,
فالسلسلة الجينية للإنسان القديم، حوالي 3 بلايين من الأجواز الرئيسية،
but an elephant and mammoth genome
ولكن جينوم الفيل أو الماموث
is about two billion base pairs larger, and most of that
أكبر بحوالي ال 2 بلايين ، ومعظمها
is composed of small, repetitive DNAs
مكوّن من أحماض نووية صغيرة ومتكررة
that make it very difficult to actually re-jig the entire structure of the genome.
والذي يجعل من الصعوبة إعادة هيكلة البنية الكاملة للجينوم.
So having this information allows us to answer
هذه المعلومات التي لدينا تسمح لنا بالإجابة
one of the interesting relationship questions
على السؤال الأكثر أهمية
between mammoths and their living relatives,
عن العلاقة بين الماموث وأقرابئه الأحياء،
the African and the Asian elephant,
الأفيال الأفريقية والآسيوية،
all of which shared an ancestor seven million years ago,
والتي جميعها تشاركت بسلفٍ واحد حوالي ال 7 ملايين سنة مضت،
but the genome of the mammoth shows it to share
ولكن السلسلة الجنية للماموث تبيّن أنه قد شارك
a most recent common ancestor with Asian elephants
بأحدث سلف مشترك له مع الفيل الآسيوي
about six million years ago,
حوالي ال6 ملايين سنة مضت،
so slightly closer to the Asian elephant.
لذلك فهو أقرب بشكل طفيف إلى الفيل الآسيوي.
With advances in ancient DNA technology,
مع التقدم بتكنلوجيا الحمض النويي القديم،
we can actually now start to begin to sequence
يمننا فعلاً الآن البدء بتسلسل
the genomes of those other extinct mammoth forms that I mentioned,
الجينوم للأشكال المختلفة من الماموث المنقرضة التي ذكرتها،
and I just wanted to talk about two of them,
وقد كنت أريد أن أتحدث عن اثنين منهم،
the woolly and the Columbian mammoth,
الماموث الصوفيّ والماموث الكولومبي،
both of which were living very close to each other
الاثنان الذان كانا يعيشان قريبين من بعضهما
during glacial peaks,
خلال فترات ذروة الأنهار الجليدي،
so when the glaciers were massive in North America,
لذا عندما كان هذه التحركات الجليدية شديدة في شمال أميركا،
the woollies were pushed into these subglacial ecotones,
انسحب الماموث الصوفيّ الى المناطق الأقل خطورة،
and came into contact with the relatives living to the south,
وبالتالي ليلتقي بأقربائه في الجنوب،
and there they shared refugia,
وهناك تشاركو بالملجأ،
and a little bit more than the refugia, it turns out.
وأكثر قليلاً من الملجأ، كما اتضح.
It looks like they were interbreeding.
يبدو أنهم كانو يتزاوجون.
And that this is not an uncommon feature
وهذا ليس بالأمر النادر
in Proboscideans, because it turns out
عند ال Proboscideans، لأنه كما اتضح
that large savanna male elephants will outcompete
ذكور فيلة السافانا الضخمة سوف تهزم
the smaller forest elephants for their females.
منافسيها فيلة الغابات الأصغر حجماً على إناثهن.
So large, hairless Columbians
فالماموث الكولومبي الضخم ذو الشعر
outcompeting the smaller male woollies.
يهزم الماموث الصوفي الأصغر حجماً.
It reminds me a bit of high school, unfortunately.
هذا يذكرني قليلاً بالمدرسة الثانوية، للأسف !
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So this is not trivial, given the idea that we want
إذاً إنها ليست أمراً سخيفاً، نظراً لفكرة أننا نريد
to revive extinct species, because it turns out
إحياء الأنواع المنقرضة، لأنه وكما يبدو
that an African and an Asian elephant
فيل أفريقي وفيل آسيوي
can actually interbreed and have live young,
يمكنهم أن يتزاوجوا وينجبوا صغاراً،
and this has actually occurred by accident in a zoo
وقد حصل هذا فعلاً عن طريق الصدفة في حديقة حيوان
in Chester, U.K., in 1978.
في تشيستر، المملكة المتحدة عام 1978.
So that means that we can actually take Asian elephant chromosomes,
هذا يعني أنه يمكننا أخذ كروموزومات الفيل الآسيوي
modify them into all those positions we've actually now
وتعديلهم إلى كل تلك الأوضاع التي، فعلاً الآن
been able to discriminate with the mammoth genome,
نحن قادرون على أن نميزهم عن جينوم الماموث،
we can put that into an enucleated cell,
يمكننا وضع ذلك داخل خلية منزوعة النواة،
differentiate that into a stem cell,
وتحويلها إلى خلية جذعية،
subsequently differentiate that maybe into a sperm,
بعد ذلك تحويلها ربما الى نطفة،
artificially inseminate an Asian elephant egg,
وثم التلقيح المصطنع لبويضة فيل آسيوي بها،
and over a long and arduous procedure,
وبعد عملية طويلة وشاقة،
actually bring back something that looks like this.
سنعيد الى الوجود شيئاً يبدو كهذا !
Now, this wouldn't be an exact replica,
حسناً، إنه لن يكون نسخة مطابقة،
because the short DNA fragments that I told you about
لأن أجزاء الحمض النووي الصغيرة التي قلت لكم عنها
will prevent us from building the exact structure,
ستمنعنا من بناء نفس الهيكل بالضبط،
but it would make something that looked and felt
ولكنه سيبدو كشيئ يشبه حقاً
very much like a woolly mammoth did.
و بشكل كبير الماموث الصوفيّ.
Now, when I bring up this with my friends,
طيب، عندما أتحدث من أصدقائي عن هذا الأمر،
we often talk about, well, where would you put it?
غالباً ما نسأل : حسناً، أين ستضعه ؟
Where are you going to house a mammoth?
أين ستُسكِن ماموثاً ؟
There's no climates or habitats suitable.
لا توجد مساكن ولا بيئة ملائمة.
Well, that's not actually the case.
حسناً، هذا ليس صحيحاً.
It turns out that there are swaths of habitat
وجدنا أن هناك مساحات ملائمة
in the north of Siberia and Yukon
في شمالي سيبيريا و يوكون
that actually could house a mammoth.
وهي ملائمة فعلاً للماموث.
Remember, this was a highly plastic animal
وتذكّر أن هذا الحيوان مرن جداً
that lived over tremendous climate variation.
وقد عاش خلال تغيرات مناخية هائلة.
So this landscape would be easily able to house it,
إذا فهذا الموقع سيكون ملائماً وسهلاً ليستضيفه،
and I have to admit that there [is] a part of the child in me,
وعليّ أن اعترف أن ذلك الطفل الموجود داخلي،
the boy in me, that would love to see
الصبيّ الموجود داخلي، يحب أن يرى
these majestic creatures walk across the permafrost
هذه الكائنات الشاهقة تمشي على الأراضي الدائمة التجمد
of the north once again, but I do have to admit
في الشمال مرة أخرى، ولكني سأعترف
that part of the adult in me sometimes wonders
الشخص البالغ داخلي يفكّر أحياناً
whether or not we should.
إن كان ينبغي علينا فعل هذا الأمر، أم لا.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Ryan Phelan: Don't go away.
ريان فالين: لا تذهب.
You've left us with a question.
لدينا سؤال.
I'm sure everyone is asking this. When you say, "Should we?"
إني متأكدة أننا جميعا نفكر به، عندما تقول : هل ينبغي علينا ؟
it feels like you're reticent there,
بدوت وكأنك متحفّظ على الأمر،
and yet you've given us a vision of it being so possible.
ولكنك تركتنا نشعر وكأنه ممكن أن يحصل جداً.
What's your reticence?
على ماذا تتحفّظ ؟
Hendrik Poinar: I don't think it's reticence.
هندريك بوينار: لا أعتقد أنه تحفّظ.
I think it's just that we have to think very deeply
أعتقد أنه يجب أن نفكّر بشكل عميق
about the implications, ramifications of our actions,
في تداعيات وعواقب أعمالنا،
and so as long as we have good, deep discussion
ومادمنا دائما نقوم بالنقاشات البنّائة
like we're having now, I think
كالتي نقوم بها اليوم. أعتقد
we can come to a very good solution as to why to do it.
يمكننا أن نصل إلى سببٍ جيد يجعلنا نقوم بهذا الأمر.
But I just want to make sure that we spend time
ولكنني أريد أن أتأكد أننا نمضي وقتاً كافياً
thinking about why we're doing it first.
نفكّر بسبب قيامنا بذلك .
RP: Perfect. Perfect answer. Thank you very much, Hendrik.
ريان: جواب رائع، شكراً جزيلاً لك، هندريك.
HP: Thank you. (Applause)
هندريك: شكراً لكم. (تصفيق)